{"tossups": [{"question": "This country's capital was called \"big-headed\" and nicknamed \"Red\" under its first Social Democratic mayor in 1918. This country's Fatherland Front absorbed its <em>Heimwehren</em> [[HAIM-veh-rehn]] and <em>Landbund</em> [[LAHND-boond]] parties. This country's civil war, known as the February Uprising, featured a suspension of parliament by Engelbert Dollfuss. Kurt Schuschnigg [[SHOOSH-nig]] moved this country politically to the right before it was seized in the Anschluss [[AHN-shlooss]]. Treated as part of Germany in World War Two, for the point, what is this European nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Austria</u></b> (accept <b><u>\u00d6sterreich</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "While working for this organization, William Fisher adopted the name Rudolf Abel. Members of this organization's Laboratory 12 manufactured the ricin [[RAI-sin]] pellet used to murder Georgi Markov. Robert Hanssen revealed the existence of Operation Monopoly to this organization. This organization, which grew out of the NKVD, included a \"Fifth Directorate'' created by Yuri Andropov to eliminate dissenters. The Foreign Intelligence Service evolved from, for the point, what Soviet intelligence agency?", "answer": "<b><u>KGB</u></b> (accept <b><u>Komitet Gosudarstvennoy Bezopasnosti</u></b>; accept <b><u>Committee for</u></b> <b><u>State Security</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this country in 752, Bodhisena [[BOH-dee-SEH-nah]] performed a lavish ceremony which used up much of this country's bronze to create a giant Vairocana statue of Buddha. The <em>Kaifuso</em> [[kai-FOO-soh]] and <em>Kojiki</em> were written in this country, the location of the Emi Rebellion. This country's Nara dynasty imported Chinese culture, modeling its capital after Chang'an. For the point, name this island nation whose legendary first kingdom was founded by a grandson of Ameratsu, Emperor Jimmu.", "answer": "<b><u>Japan</u></b> (or <b><u>Nippon</u></b>-koku; or <b><u>Nihon</u></b>-koku)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This person may have cut funding to the Society of Beneficence, because they elected another president. In order to visit Francisco Franco and Antonio Salazar without repercussions, this person organized the \"Rainbow Tour\" of Europe. This person was named \"Spiritual Leader of the Nation\" just one month before dying of cervical cancer. This woman coined the name <em>descamisados</em> for her husband's shirtless supporters. For the point, name this Argentinian actress who rose to power with her husband, Juan.", "answer": "<b><u>E</u></b>va <b><u>Peron</u></b> (accept Maria Eva <b><u>Duarte</u></b>; accept <b><u>Evita</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This empire built the Tower of Skulls at Borj-er-Rous. The Patriarch of Aquileia [[ah-kwee-LAY-ah]] fought this empire in a battle in which defenders were called \"inglorious\" by Venetian writer, Nicol\u00f2 Zen the Younger. At another battle, Occhiali led this empire with a fleet of galleys. Besides Preveza [[preh-VEH-tsah]] and Djerba [[ZHER-bah]], this Empire fought Don Juan de Austria and the Catholic Holy League at the Battle of Lepanto. For the point, name this Turkish empire which effectively dissolved in 1922.", "answer": "<b><u>Ottoman</u></b> Empire (accept <b><u>Ottoman</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One leader of this denomination opposed Andreas Osiander and Flacius [[FLAK-ee-us]] and printed a paraphrase of Ptolemy's <em>Tetrabiblos</em>. That leader of this denomination authored <em>Treatise of the Power and Primacy of the Pope</em> and the <em>Apology of the Augsburg</em> <em>Confession</em>. An intellectual network of this denomination including Caspar Peucer [[PYOO-sur]] was Philip Melanchton's circle at the University of Wittenberg. The author of the <em>Ninety-five Theses</em> founded, for the point, what branch of Protestantism?", "answer": "<b><u>Lutheran</u></b>ism (or <b><u>Lutheran</u></b>s; prompt on \"Luther\"; prompt on Protestant \"Reformation\" or \"Protestant(ism)\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A group of pirates called the Ulcinian Sea Wolves were from this country, where the Vulnetari [[vool-neh-TAH-ree]] volunteers and Balli Komb\u00ebtar [[kohm-BEH-tahr]] originated. In World War Two, Myslim Peza [[MEE-zlim PEH-zah]] helped found this European country's National Liberation Movement. Francesco Jacomoni [[zhah-koh-MOH-nee]] served as governor of this country, and Queen Geraldine Apponyi and her son, Leka I, were forced to flee from this nation to England. Enver Hoxha [[HAHDJ-uh]] and Zog I both led this country, which Italy invaded in 1939. For the point, name this Balkan country.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Albania</u></b> (accept <b><u>Shqip</u></b>\u00ebria)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this war, a shell loaded with two flags and a Christmas pudding was fired. In this war, \"chevril\" [[cheh-VREEL]] became the main foodstuff for soldiers who were besieged at Ladysmith under the command of Redvers Buller. This war included battles at Spion Kop and Colenso, and a treaty signed at Melrose House, the Treaty of Vereeniging [[fuh-REE-nuh-kung]], ended this war which began after the Jameson Raid. For the point, what was this 1899-1902 war between the British and two Dutch-speaking republics?", "answer": "Second <b><u>Boer</u></b> War (accept Anglo-<b><u>Boer</u></b> War; accept <b><u>South African</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This natural resource allowed the Oklo Mine in Gabon to produce self-sustaining power nearly 2 billion years ago. The Obama administration controversially authorized the sale of a company to Russia which mined for this resource. It was suggested during the Iraq disarmament crisis that Saddam Hussein attempted to purchase this resource in its \"yellowcake\" form. The primary agent used in the bomb dropped on Hiroshima, for the point, what is this radioactive element whose 235-isotope is used for nuclear power?", "answer": "<b><u>Uranium</u></b> (accept <b><u>U</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Actors Jeff Goldblum and Clint Eastwood are aficionados of this instrument which Bill Evans played on Miles Davis\u2019s classic album, <em>Kind of Blue</em>. Vladimir Horowitz amazed Rachmaninoff with his virtuosic solo in that composer\u2019s <em>Third Concerto</em> for this instrument. Glenn Gould was a notoriously idiosyncratic player of this instrument, rejecting the classics written by Chopin and Liszt and humming to himself while playing. Commonly known by only a portion of its full name, for the point, what is this instrument whose full name translates to \"soft loud\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Piano</u></b>forte", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Rulers of what is today this country imprisoned people at the Mountain of the Princes. One of the rulers in the region that is today this country was named Gudit while another, Mararah, was a general of Dil Na'od [[DEEL nah-OHD]]. Michael VIII was sent giraffes from this country's leader Yekuno Amlak. This country's city of Lalibela [[lah-lee-BEH-lah]] was the capital of the Zagwe Dynasty. Known for its Kingdom of Aksum and the Solomonic Dynasty, for the point, what is this East African nation once ruled by Haile Selassie?", "answer": "Federal Democratic Republic of <b><u>Ethiopia</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ethiopia</u></b>n Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's successor won the Battles of Mursa Major and Mons Seleucus [[seh-LOO-kus]]. This man beat a rival in the Balkans at the Battle of Mardia, and he won at Cibalae [[SEE-bah-lay]] after appointing his brother Bassianus as <em>caesar</em>. This leader defeated Licinius [[lai-SIN-ee-us]] at the Battle of Chrysopolis [[krih-SOP-oh-liss]], leading to the end of the Tetrarchy. In a meeting on the Tiber, this man inspired his troops with the <em>Chi Rho</em> [[KAI-ROH]] symbol, defeating Maxentius at the Battle of the Milvian Bridge. For the point, name this first Christian Roman emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>Constantine</u></b> the Great (accept <b><u>Constantine</u></b> I; accept Flavius Velerius <b><u>Constantinus</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Sites in this country were excavated by Catherine Jarrige [[jah-REEZH]] and Jean-Francois Jarrige. Hellmut de Terra identified this country's Soanian culture, and archaeologists have been able to label four Mehrgarh [[MEHR-gar]] periods through sites in this modern country. An ancient site in this country has a \"College Hall\", a \"Great Granary,\" and a \"Great Bath,\" and was where a 4500-year old bronze \"Dancing Girl\" was found. For the point, name this country, the location of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro in the Indus River Valley.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of <b><u>Pakistan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One artist from this country created <em>The Pink Wall</em>, which was recovered from Nazi war criminal Kurt Gerstein [[GER-shtine]]. After a 1905 exhibition, one critic said, \"A pot of paint has been flung in the face of the public,\" referring to paintings from this country. An artist from this country painted <em>Woman with a Hat</em>, which was later bought by Gertrude Stein. Another artist from this country founded the Impressionist movement with his painting, <em>Impression, Sunrise</em>. For the point, name this home country of the Fauvist painter Henri Matisse.", "answer": "<b><u>France</u></b> (or <b><u>French</u></b> Republic; accept <b><u>French</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An island on this river had phases of civilization known as the Formiga and the Ananatuba. A culture on this river was studied by Charles C. Mann and Anna Curtenius Roosevelt. Betty Meggers claimed that a civilization on an island in this river collapsed in 1400. That island in this river, Maraj\u00f3 [[mah-rah-HOH]], was one of the few locations in the world to avoid the Spanish Flu epidemic of 1918. Francisco de Orellana [[oh-reh-YAH-nah]] studied this river on which Manaus had a rubber boom. For the point, name this South American river.", "answer": "<b><u>Amazon</u></b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In 1950, Hayashi Yoken burned down this city's <em>Kinkaku-ji</em>, or Temple of the Golden Pavilion. A path in this city is lined with over one thousand gates, most of which have been donated by businessmen to honor the goddess Inari. In 1928, the <em>Yata no Kagami</em> mirror and the other pieces of the Imperial Regalia of Japan were transported to this former capital city for the enthronement of the Showa Emperor. For the point, name this city which served as the capital of Japan until 1868, when it was moved to Tokyo.", "answer": "<b><u>Kyoto</u></b> City (or <b><u>Kyoto</u></b>-shi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This province was home to a Quaker sect called Children of Peace, or \"Davidites.\" This province contained the headquarters of the Reform Movement, which was followed by the Clear Grits. One of the world's first divided highways was this province's Queen Elizabeth Way. The Family Compact participated in the Upper Canada Rebellion in this province in 1837. During the War of 1812, Americans burned this province's largest city, at the time named York. For the point, name this most-populous Canadian province.", "answer": "<b><u>Ontario</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country faced the Night Frost crisis during the tenure of prime minister Karl-August Fagerholm [[FAH-gah-holm]]. German-trained J\u00e4gers [[YAY-gahs]] made up much of the White Guard during this country's 1918 Civil War. This country's Agrarian League was led by \"active neutrality\" under Urho Kekkonen [[OOR-hoh KEH-koh-nen]]. After the Interim Peace, the Salpa and VKT lines defended this country, which were much stronger than the Mannerheim Line. Ceding Karelia after losing the Winter War, for the point, what is this country in which the Helsinki Accords were signed?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Finland</u></b> (accept <b><u>Suomi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During an event in this city, one thinker claimed that no one should fear death and argued that his portrayal in <em>The Clouds</em> had turned public opinion against him. During that event in this city, that philosopher compared himself to a gadfly while speaking to Meletus [[meh-LAY-tus]] about the charges of impiety he faced. As a youth, Aristotle traveled to this city to study at Plato's <em>Academy</em>. For the point, name this city in which Socrates was convicted of corrupting the youth by a democratic government.", "answer": "<b><u>Athens</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "During the Council of Clermont, Pope Urban II called for this action after a Byzantine emperor asked for military aid against the Seljuk Turks. In support of this action, Peter the Hermit traveled throughout Europe, encouraging nobles and common people alike to share in this enterprise. On the way to their ultimate objective during this conflict, Christian warriors captured Nicaea and Antioch. For the point, what 11th century holy war ended with the successful occupation of Jerusalem?", "answer": "<b><u>First Crusade</u></b> (prompt on <b><u>Crusade</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A region of this country was the location of a FLEC attack on Togo's national football team. This country's Battle of Death Road occurred during Operation Savannah at Quifangondo [[kwee-fahn-GAHN-doh]]. Peasants in this country fought cotton planters in the Baixa de Cassanje [[BAI-shah deh KAHS-ahn-yay]] revolt. South African Defense Forces repeatedly entered this country, fighting in the Battle of Cuito Cuanavale [[KWEE-toh kwah-nah-VAH-leh]]. During this country's war for independence, Jonas Savimbi and Agostinho Neto fought against Portugal. For the point, the MPLA has governed from Luanda in which country?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Angola</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Converted into a stage work by Julie Taymor, the Broadway version of this movie won six Tony Awards including Best Musical in 1998, and is notable as the first Disney musical to be based on an original story. Jeremy Irons won an Annie Award for his voice work as the villain in this 1994 film which received the Golden Globe for Best Motion Picture, Musical or Comedy. Composer Hans Zimmer joined Tim Rice and Elton John to produce the score of, for the point, what Disney musical film which tells the story of the betrayal of Mufasa and Simba\u2019s coming of age?", "answer": "The <b><u>Lion King</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A celebration for this person was the site of the first use of a rotating camera which could take panning shots. A sun beam landing on this person's head was interpreted as divine favor by Queen Liliuokalani [[lih-lyoo-kah-LAH-nee]]. Abdul Karim, \"the Munshi,\" served this person, and this figure's husband, who was from Coburg, helped set up the Great Exhibition. An international gala was set up during this figure's 1887 Golden Jubilee. For the point, name this long-ruling queen of England.", "answer": "<b><u>Victoria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The writer of one 1935 poem echoes the refrain that this country \u201cnever was\u201d [this country] \u201cto me.\u201d In a different poem, published in 1926 at the height of a \"renaissance\" in this country, the same writer tells his oppressors, \u201cThey\u2019ll see how beautiful I am / And be ashamed,\" and concludes, \"I, too, am [this country].\" That author from this country first gained notice in <em>The Crisis</em>, a periodical written by an organization dedicated to helping people of color in this country to overcome adversity. For the point, what country was home to Langston Hughes and the Harlem Renaissance?", "answer": "<b><u>United States</u></b> of America (accept <b><u>US</u></b>A; accept <b><u>America</u></b>; accept \"Let <b><u>America</u></b> Be America Again\"; accept \"I, Too, Sing <b><u>America</u></b>\")", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "Rebels in this country, in opposition to conversion to the metric system, led the \"revolt of the kilogram breaker,\" or Quebra-Quilos [[KEH-brah KEE-lohs]]. This country was rocked by the 1842 Liberal Rebellions, and it faced a 1798 social revolution called the Revolt of the Tailors. Landowners fought settlers in this country's Contestado War. This country faced the Praieira [[prah-YEH-rah]] revolt in its region of Pernambuco [[pehr-nahm-BOO-koh]]. Getulio Vargas governed this country during the Estado Novo period. For the point, name this country, whose Bandeirantes [[bahn-deh-RAHN-tehs]] explorers hailed from S\u00e3o Paulo.", "answer": "Federative Republic of <b><u>Brazil</u></b> (accept Empire of <b><u>Brazil</u></b>; accept United Kingdom of Portugal, <b><u>Brazil</u></b>, and the Algarves)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In what is today this country, the \"Coolie Ordinance\" allowed for the \"penal sanction.\" Many STOVIA doctors helped fight for the independence of this country which was governed via the \"Ethical Policy.\" In this country, Vitamin B1's relationship to beriberi was identified, and Europeans first documented the Komodo dragon in 1910. A Dutch writer pen-named Multatuli [[MOOL-tah-TOO-lee]] wrote <em>Max Havelaar</em> about the Java coffee trade in this modern country. For the point, name this former Dutch colony.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Indonesia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man names four parks in Chicago, including one nicknamed Bughouse Square. This man names a double-arched bridge which crosses the Harlem River. This man names a prestigious university in St. Louis and is memorialized with an obelisk capped with aluminum. The largest city named for this man sits in federal territory originally taken from Virginia and Maryland. For the point, give the namesake of a Pacific Northwest state which is home to Seattle.", "answer": "George <b><u>Washington</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 1229 student strike at a university in this city began on Shrove Tuesday and ended when Gregory IX issued the bull <em>Parens scientiarum</em> [[PAH-rens see-en-TAH-room]]. A college in this city was the origin of the slogan \"Under the paving stones, the beach.\" A medieval school in this city had four \"nations\" with a set number of students from Pignerol [[pee-neh-ROHL]] and Flanders. Philip II chartered a university in this city named for Robert de Sorbon. For the point, name this city in which Voltaire studied.", "answer": "<b><u>Paris</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A leader of this country was originally urged to run for office by organizations including Kamel Gemilak [[KAH-mel JEM-ee-lahk]]. This country's Tahrir [[tah-REER]] Square hosted major pro-democracy protests leading to a 2011 revolution. Arab Spring protests in this country forced Hosni Mubarak to resign. In 2014, 97% of the voters in this country were reported to have selected former Minister of Defense Abdel Fattah el-Sisi as president. Sisi led a coup against Mohamed Morsi in, for the point, what North African country?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Egypt</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "During this conflict, the <em>Couronne</em> escorted a ship under the command of Raphael Semmes [[SIMZ]] away from a harbor in the prelude to the Battle of Cherbourg [[SHEHR-boorg]]. Charles Wilkes caused an international incident during this conflict after seizing two envoys aboard the HMS <em>Trent</em>. One side in this conflict attempted to garner international support by appealing to \"King Cotton.\" For the point, name this conflict in which diplomats attempted to convince Britain and France to support the Confederate States of America.", "answer": "U.S. <b><u>Civil War</u></b> (accept American <b><u>Civil War</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person signed an accord with Sheikh Abdullah of Kashmir and crushed the Mizo rebellion in Mizoram [[MEE-zo-rahm]]. This leader authorized Operation Meghdoot to capture the Siachen [[SEE-ah-chen] Glacier. Under this leader, the \"Smiling Buddha\" nuclear test was conducted, and between 1975 and 1977, this ruler governed by decree in \"The Emergency.\" After taking over the Golden Temple in Operation Blue Star, this woman's Sikh bodyguards killed her. For the point, name this first female prime minister of India.", "answer": "<b><u>I</u></b>ndira <b><u>Gandhi</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}